## Jenny Leopoldina Smith, MSc

Email: JennyL.Smith12@gmail.com Phone: (603) 801-9876

Code: github.com/jennylsmith Linkedin.com/in/jenny-leopoldina-smith

Computational biologist and R programmer applying methods in data science and data engineering to biomedical research. Expertise of over 8 years in genomics and next generation sequencing (NGS) data.

#### **Work Experience**

### Computational Biologist, Senior April 2022 – Sept 2024

Seattle Children's, Seattle, WA Research Scientific Computing Dept.

- Develop and adapte reproducible genomics workflows using Nextflow and nfcore tools for RNA-seq quantification, Cut&Run, ATAC-seq, and PacBio Isoseq; enabled use of containerized software with singularity/apptainer and the PBSpro executor on a high-performance compute cluster (HPC).
- Analysis and visualization of multi-sample scRNA-seq and scATAC-seq datasets with Cellranger quantification, followed by doublet detection, ambient DNA correction, dataset integration (SCANVI and Seurat v4/v5). Production of multiomics analyses for bulk transcriptomic and single-cell datasets using dplyr and tidyverse principles.
- Generation of complex visualizations include heatmaps, circos plots, oncoprints, 3D scatter plots, genomic tracks, network graphs, and volcano plots, among others, to identify actionable insights from multivariate biological datasets from NGS and public databases (ensembl, UCSC, Genomic Data Commons).
- Engagement in bioinformatics support by providing guidance and troubleshooting assistance at office hours and teaching internal courses.

### Bioinformatics Analyst January 2017 – March 2022

Fred Hutchinson Cancer Center, Seattle, WA Principal Investigator: Dr. Soheil Meshinchi

- Developed Nextflow pipelines using docker for cloud computing on AWS and with singularity for on-prem HPC; processed 1000's of RNA-seq samples for gene expression quantification and fusion detection.
- Established a lab github organization at github.com/Meshinchi-Lab.
- Created an R package (DeGSEA) using Roxygen and 'usethis' framework to streamline the association of clinical covariates and RNA-seq expression data.
- Profiled pediatric AML subtypes defined by gene fusions and mutations using RNA-sequencing with supervised and unsupervised clustering ML algorithms, statistical regression and classification, in a multidisciplinary environment with biologists, bioinformaticians, clinicians, and lead investigators.

## Postbaccalaureate Fellow June 2014 - June 2016

National Institutes of Health, *Bethesda, MD Principal Investigator:* Dr. Maria Morasso

• Investigated the function of homeodomain protein DLX3 in keratinocytes at NIAMS. Bioinformatics analysis of ATAC-seq and ChIP-seq (peak calling, motif enrichment, NGS.plot, Deeptools) from knock-out murine models.

### **Languages and Software**

- R programming: base R, Tidyverse, Bioconductor, R package development, Quarto, Rmarkdown
- Bash/linux shell scripting
- **Nextflow** workflow language
- Python: scripting and Snakemake pipelines
- Git version control
- Github and bitbucket
- PBS/SLURM HPC schedulers
- **Containerization**: docker, singularity, apptainer
- Amazon Web Services: AWS S3 and Batch
- Jira and agile framework, Atlassian products
- CI/CD with Bamboo

#### NGS Data Types

- scRNA-seq (single-cell)
- scATAC-seq (single-cell)
- RNA-seq Illumina, PacBio
- ATAC-seq
- miRNA-seq
- Cut&Run
- ChIP-seq

#### **Bioinformatics Analysis**

- scRNA-seq and scATAC-seq differential expression and celltype classification
- RNA-seq differential expression
- RNA-seq Fusion detection
- RNA-seq long reads (PacBio)
- DNA Motif analysis

## Jenny Leopoldina Smith, MSc

Email: JennyL.Smith12@gmail.com Phone: (603) 801-9876

Code: github.com/jennylsmith Linkedin.com/in/jenny-leopoldina-smith

### **Education**

Applied Bioinformatics and Genomics, M.Sc.

University of Oregon, Eugene, OR

**Biology, B.A.**, magna cum laude University of San Diego, San Diego, CA June 2016 - September 2017

August 2008 – May 2012

## Genome wide differential binding and accessibility

- DNA variant calling
- Genomic alignments
- NGS quality control

#### **Publications**

- Le, Q., Hadland, B., Smith, J. L.,... Meshinchi, S. CBFA2T3-GLIS2 model of pediatric acute megakaryoblastic leukemia identifies FOLR1 as a CAR T cell target. *Journal of Clinical Investigation*. 2024. DOI:10.1172/jci184305
- Bertrums, E. J. M.\*, Smith, J. L.\*, Harmon, L.\*, ... Meshinchi, S. Comprehensive molecular and clinical characterization of NUP98 fusions in pediatric acute myeloid leukemia. *Haematologica*. 2023. DOI:10.3324/haematol.2022.281653
- Farrar, J. E., Smith, J. L., Othus, M., ... Meshinchi, S. Long Noncoding RNA Expression Independently Predicts Outcome in Pediatric Acute Myeloid Leukemia. *Journal of Clinical Oncology.* 2023. DOI:10.1200/jco.22.01114
- Le, Q., Hadland, B., **Smith, J. L.,** Leonti, A., ... Meshinchi, S. CBFA2T3-GLIS2 model of pediatric acute megakaryoblastic leukemia identifies FOLR1 as a CAR T cell target. *Journal of Clinical Investigation*. **2022**. DOI:10.1172/jci157101
- Huang, B. J., Smith, J. L., Farrar, J. E., ... Meshinchi, S. Integrated stem cell signature and cytomolecular risk determination in pediatric acute myeloid leukemia. *Nature Communications.* 2022. DOI:10.1038/s41467-022-33244-6
- Smith, J.L., Ries, RE, Hylkema, ... Meshinchi, S. Comprehensive Transcriptome Profiling of Cryptic *CBFA2T3-GLIS2* Fusion-positive AML Defines Novel Therapeutic Options A COG and TARGET Pediatric AML Study. *Clinical Cancer Research.* 2019. DOI: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-19-1800

Additional Publications: <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0402-2779">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0402-2779</a>

#### **Speaker Presentations**

- IGNITE, panelist on careers in data science and technology to promote gender equity and representation in STEM. IGNITE Field Trip with Rainier Beach High School (Seattle Children's Research Institute, 2024)
- Molecular Medicine Tri-conference, panelist on AI in Genomics and Precision Medicine (San Francisco, CA, 2020).
- American Society for Hematology, oral presentation on Comprehensive Transcriptome Profiling of Cryptic CBFA2T3-GLIS2 Fusion-Positive AML Defines Novel Therapeutic Options — a COG and Target Pediatric AML Study (San Diego, CA, 2018).
- American Society for Hematology, oral presentation on The LSC17 Leukemic Stem Cell Signature Predicts Outcome in Pediatric Acute Myeloid Leukemia. Abstract Achievement Award Recipient (Atlanta, GA, 2017).

# Continuing Education and Volunteering

- IGNITE speaker to promote gender equity in STEM, Seattle Children's, 2024
- International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB) member, 2023
- RLadies event organizer, Seattle, WA, 2018-2023
- Bioconductor conference organizer, Seattle, WA, 2022
- Mentor, UO Bioinformatics and Genomics Graduate Program, 2021- 2022
- SnpReportR, Carnegie Mellon and DNAnexus Hackathon, 2021
- Pacific Biosciences Isoseq3 analysis training, 2020
- Nextflow workflow development training, 2020
- Women In Biology, MAPS Mentorship Group, 2017-2019
- ConsensusML, NCBI Hackathon, 2018
- Mentor, Fred Hutch High School Internships, 2018